<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IGRT on Zheng Zhang</title>
    <link>https://zhangresearch.org/tags/igrt/</link>
    <description>Recent content in IGRT on Zheng Zhang</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2015-{year}, Zheng Zhang, Ph.D.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://zhangresearch.org/tags/igrt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>IGPT Software Development</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/wukong-app-dev/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zhangresearch.org/project/wukong-app-dev/</guid>
      <description>As an essential component of our Image-Guided Proton Therapy (IGPT) practice, I am developing a clinical computer vision application (Code name: WuKong) for visual guidance and tumor tracking during motion-managed treatments, based on high speed acquisition and real time processing of fluoroscopic frames. Being fully DICOM-aware, this .NET/C# Windows desktop application is integrated into existing treatment planning infrastructure for medical data transfer as well as HIPAA-compliant cloud storage, and provides a user-friendly graphical interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flat-panel Detector (FPD) Calibration</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/fpd-calibration/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zhangresearch.org/project/fpd-calibration/</guid>
      <description>Precise delivery of proton treatment requires a good match between the DRR and in-room FPD imagers. Whereas the DRRs generated by the treatment planing system are based on prior CT and room specification, the actual positions of the imagers slightly deviate from the spec. This project delivers an iterative algorithmic calibration routine to correct the resulting image errors, i.e. translation, oblique rotation and timing error. By using a large custom phantom, both panels are corrected simultaneously.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>