<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Zheng Zhang, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zhangresearch.org/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2015–2020, Zheng Zhang</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zhangresearch.org/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image-guidance Software Development</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/wukong-app-dev/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangresearch.org/project/wukong-app-dev/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To augment our proton facility vendor&amp;rsquo;s hardware with the capability of fluoroscopy-based motion verification and monitoring, I am developing a computer vision application (Code name: Wukong), based on high-speed acquisition and real-time processing of flat-panel detector (FPD) data streams. Built as a fully DICOM-aware utility, this .NET/C# Windows desktop application has been integrated into existing treatment planning workflow with Varian Eclipse Scripting API. It also provides an optional ability to store live-captured fluoroscopic data on a HIPAA-compliant scalable storage cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flat-panel Detector Calibration</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/fpd-calibration/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangresearch.org/project/fpd-calibration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Accurate delivery of radiotherapy dose is predicated upon careful motion management. This is particularly true for spot-scanned proton therapy. Our proton therapy vendor developed a stereoscopic kV X-ray image-guidance platform for this purpose. While it is engineered to a given specification, the actual positions of the components (e.g. flat-panel detectors) may contain small errors. This project delivers an iterative algorithmic calibration routine to correct such errors, i.e. translation, rotation and non-affine distortions. The main motivation behind this routine is to enable high-fidelity perspective overlays of RT structure sets in our in-house clinical software. It may also be used as an independent QA of vendor&amp;rsquo;s own calibrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangresearch.org/img/project-fpd-calibration/header.png&#34; alt=&#34;Schematic 3D-2D calibration routine&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nanoconfined polymer electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://zhangresearch.org/project/nanoconfined-polymer-electrolytes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangresearch.org/project/nanoconfined-polymer-electrolytes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We probe the nanoscale viscosity and molecular structure of confined polymer electrolytes inside rigid nanovolumes, using X-ray photon correlation spectroscopy (XPCS) and grazing incidence X-ray scattering (GIWAXS), respectively. We show that gold nanoparticle as Brownian swimmers can be used to probe the nanoscale viscosity of a confined polymer melt, and that the effective viscosity is substantially different than in bulk. Our experiments take advantage of recent instrumental improvements at the Coheren Hard X-ray Scattering Beamline (CHX) at the National Synchrotron Light Source II (NSLS-II), which have yielded improved coherence, and extended beam stability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
